>> Hello. Today we're going
to discuss the
budget constraint.
Let us start with some
basic definitions.
The first definition we need to
cover is the
consumption choice set.
The consumption choice
set is a collection of
every possible consumption
option that one consumer
can possibly get unrestricted or
regardless their own budgetary
and time constraints.
But of course, people cannot
actually reach any bundle
or any choice in
that grand set because
people have limited
resources in their wallet,
in their bank
account, and in time.
The next important concept
is the consumption bundle.
A consumption bundle is a
mathematical expression,
a vector in particular,
that contains quantities of
the n goods that we can have or
we will have in our
simplified universe.
So we're going to study
a simplified universe that
consists of only n
different types of goods,
and each of these
different goods
can be consumed in
different quantities.
Let me give you an example.
Suppose we have only two goods.
It's going to be coffee
and orange juice.
We're going to denote coffee by
x_1 and orange juice by x_2.
And when we have a universe
with only these two goods,
we can form a
bundle in this way.
So this is a general expression,
a vector, a two
dimensional vector.
And for example, if this
vector takes this form 5,
7, it means that there
are five units of
coffee and seven units
of orange juice.
Suppose we are expressing
both goods in ounces,
so this would mean
five ounces of coffee
and seven ounces
of orange juice.
If we would have in a
different example now
three goods for let's
say x_1 again coffee,
x_2 orange juice, and
let's say x_3 pizza,
then this one will be in slices
and these two in ounces.
An example of a bundle here
would be, for example,
again, 5, 7, 2.
This would be five
ounces of coffee,
seven ounces of orange juice,
and two slices of pizza.
This would be a bundle.
Also, we have
to take into consideration
the prices of the goods,
and that is given
by another vector
that we will denote
p_1 through p_n and,
we will do examples in
a second with that.
So let's discuss now
a new concept that we will
call affordable bundles.
So affordable bundles
are the bundles that
given prices and given your
income, you can afford.
So it would be, in other words,
bundles that given prices
you face and the
income you have,
you can purchase with
the income you have.
The equation to find
the bundles that you
can afford that are
within your budget constraints
are given by this inequality.
The first term here, p_1x_1,
is the amount you will spend
an x in good one all the
way to the amount you
would spend in good n,
and all that expenditure
summed up or added
up needs to be equal or
below the income you have.
Let us do an example.
Suppose we have as
before x_1 coffee,
x_2 orange juice, and
x_3 pizza and we
have that the price of coffee
is one dollar per ounce,
the price of orange
juice is going to
be point $0.5 per ounce,
and the price of
one slice of pizza is
going to be three dollars.
So we have three goods: x_1
coffee, x_2 orange juice,
x_3 pizza and their
corresponding prices are one,
50 cents, and three dollars.
So the expenditure of this is
written generically like this.
This is how much you
spend in coffee,
this is how much you
spend in orange juice,
this is how much
you spend in pizza,
and together is, of course,
your total expenditure.
And as you saw from
the previous slide for
one particular bundle,
x_1, x_2, x_3,
to be affordable, this
inequality needs to hold.
The total expenditure needs to
be equal or below your income.
So let's give an example.
Let's test this.
Is this bundle affordable?
That is a question. We're going
to start with something simple.
We're going to
start with bundle x
that's going to be
one ounce of coffee,
one ounce of orange juice,
and one slice of pizza.
So let's form this
expression for our example.
It's going to be p_1,
which I hope you
remember is one,
so we have 1 times 1 because
we have one unit of
coffee plus the price of
orange juice was 0.5
times 1 because of this
plus the price of
the slice of pizza was
3 times 1 unit is this.
So the total expenditure in
this simple example
will be 1 plus 0.5,
so 1.5, plus 3,
so it's going to be 4.5.
So suppose as an example
that income is 10,
therefore this bundle 1, 1,
1, i affordable.
In more technical terms,
it is this bundle is inside
our budget constraint.
Suppose instead that we
have a different bundle.
Let's say we have
bundle 5, 7, 4.
So 5 ounces of coffee,
7 ounces of orange juice,
4 slices of pizza.
Now we're going to see if
that bundle is affordable.
Remember prices are one,
price of two is 0.5,
and price of pizza was,
if I remember
correctly, yes, was $3.
And also, we said
that income was 10.
So this is your
context and I want to
test whether this bundle
here is affordable.
So let's see. So what is
the total expenditure?
Total expenditure is
1*5+0.5*7+3*4.
So this is 5,
this is 3.5 and this is 12.
As you are already realizing,
this is 17+3.5 that is 20.5.
And in this case,
this is greater than 10,
so the bundle 5,
7, 4 is not affordable.
Let us now discuss the budget
line or budget constraint.
So the key concept
here is that there are
some bundles that are just
affordable in the sense
that if you buy them,
your income will be fully spent.
Let me repeat that. There
are bundles that are just
affordable in the sense
that if you buy them,
your income will be fully spent.
So mathematically, this is
expression for such bundle.
If you see here,
the total expenditure is
exactly equal to income.
In these cases, if
a bundle satisfies
that the total expenditure
of buying that particular
bundle equals income,
we say that that bundle
is on the budget line.
From now on, we're going to
focus in the world or universe
with only two commodities.
So it is true that we can have,
as in real life, in
the supermarket,
many different types of goods.
But because important
points that we will
learn only require two goods,
we're going to simplify
our discussion and focus
on the world with
only two goods.
For example, coffee
and orange juice.
In this world, the expenditure
is simply p1x1+p2x2.
And if a bundle
satisfies this equation,
which is that expenditure
equals to income,
we say that that particular
bundle is on the budget line.
So in what follows,
I'm going to teach you how
to find this budget
line mathematically.
Let us present a
diagram, a graph,
that we're going to use
many times and it's
going to help us illustrate some
of the concepts we will discuss.
This is what we call
the commodity space.
So the commodity
space in the universe
of only two goods
is just a plane.
And it's a bi-dimensional plane
with two axis, x1 and x2.
And this for example will
refer to quantities of
coffee and this for example will
refer to quantities
of orange juice.
This is an example. It can
be any pair of two goods.
In this universe or in this
so-called commodity space,
there will be bundles
that we can afford,
we can purchase with our
income and there are
bundles that are not affordable
or we cannot purchase.
So there will be for example,
bundles that if they
are too expensive,
because they contain way
too many units of goods 1 and 2,
will not be affordable.
And there will be other bundles,
especially those that
contain few units,
that will be affordable.
But how do we know in
a synthesized and precise way
which bundles are affordable
and which bundles
are not affordable.
That is determined by what we
call the budgeted
and the budget line.
So let's start discussing
the budget line.
The budget line as I
mentioned earlier,
it has this equation,
income equals expenditure.
So we're going to discuss
the budget line mathematically
and also graphically.
Let's do this. Suppose you
only spend your money in good 1.
Let's say this, only by x1.
If you do that it means that
x2 is zero and it means
that your budget line
only has this expression
because x2 is zero.
And therefore,
[NOISE] the maximum
amount of x1 that you can
purchase is going to be this.
Right from here to here
we're just solving for x1.
Similarly, if we only buy x2,
that means that we are
setting x1 as zero.
And in that case the max amount
of good 2 I could buy
is given by this.
It's putting all your
money only on good 2.
We call these guys, intercepts.
And the reason why we
call them intercepts
is going to become
apparent in a second,
but it's mainly
because those are
the points that the budget
line crosses the axis.
So now let us put those
concepts together.
Let's draw again
our two dimensional
commodity space x_1, x_2.
And let's see what the budget
line means for this space.
We want to draw
this line into this space.
That's what we want to do.
So you might be thinking,
this is the y axis,
this is the x axis,
I can solve for x_2
and that is correct.
You could solve for x_2 and
you will do the following.
You would find that x_2
= m/p_2-p_1/p_2*x_1.
From here to here,
the only thing I'm doing
is I'm solving for x_2.
Again, from the
top to the bottom,
the only thing I'm doing
is I'm solving for x_2.
So you have learned in
previous courses how to
draw lines in a
bidimensional plane.
And you will remember that this
is exactly what we were calling
the intercept and this thing
here is going to be the slope.
So we're going to bring that
information into this here.
Since prices are positive,
we know this slope is negative.
So if we have an
intercept here like this,
the budget line is going to be
negative and is going
to go somewhere else.
So we know that this slope
equals -p_1/p_2,
and the only thing
that remains to be
found is this intercept.
But that intercept means that
what is the amount I will
purchase of x_1 if
I buy zero of x_2,
which we have actually
solved before.
It is right here.
So we also have that
solution already and that
will be income divided by p_1.
So to wrap up,
we have found three things.
We have found the intercept
in the y axis or x_2,
we have found the slope,
and we have found the
intercept in the x axis,
which is for x_1.
What is also interesting is that
this so called budget line
is dividing the whole
commodity space
in two different regions.
One region is the region
of affordable bundles.
That is all these that I'm
highlighting right now,
all the thing here,
and of course everything
that is inside.
This is what we call
the budget set.
So we can afford all the
bundles that show up here,
all the points that are here,
those are points
that we can afford.
But the same thing is doing
for bundles that are outside.
Bundles that are outside
are not reachable.
We cannot buy these points.
Those will imply expenditure
that is above our means,
above our income.
This here is just the graph
borrowed from our textbook
and it depicts the
same thing we have
been discussing on the
whiteboard or blackboard.
Some of you might be asking,
but what if there are
more than two goods?
Can I still draw that?
And the answer is yes.
You can still draw
the budget set and
the budget surface up
to three commodities,
which is what is depicted here.
The intercepts are the same
as before in the sense
that for x_1 is m/p_1
and for x_2 is m/p_2,
and for x_3 is m/p_3.
However, the question
of course now has
three elements in the
side of the expenditure.
And instead of being
a budget line,
it's now a budget plane
or a budget surface.
Let us do one example.
So suppose income is 100,
p_1 is $3, and p_2= $1.
So let's see how we will
draw this budget line.
First, as always,
we need to start with
drawing the axis x_1, x_2.
And then we need to
find the intercepts.
So one intercept is m/3,
which is 100/3 in this case,
income divided by p_1.
And we're going to do
this one somewhere here.
So this is going to be m/p_1.
In this case, this
is equal 200/3.
And in the other case,
we're going to do this up here.
For good 2 it is going
to be m/p_2 = 100/1,
which in this case
is going to be,
of course, just 100.
So the budget line is
the line that connects
these two intercepts.
So 100/3 and simply 100.
And we know more than that.
We know that the slope
is going to be -p_1/p_2,
which in this case is simply -3.